<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at Torceter in the countie of Northampton the 8. of Iune, Anno Dom. 1588. at the visitation of the right reuerend Father in God, the Bishop of Peeterborow, by Iohn Beatniffe preacher of the woord of God in Brackley.</title>
            <author>Beatniffe, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1590</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 35 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06135</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1662</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116644</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851860</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851860</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17152</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06135)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17152)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 307:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at Torceter in the countie of Northampton the 8. of Iune, Anno Dom. 1588. at the visitation of the right reuerend Father in God, the Bishop of Peeterborow, by Iohn Beatniffe preacher of the woord of God in Brackley.</title>
                  <author>Beatniffe, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[38] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Charlewood for Roger VVard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1590.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B C⁴ (-C4).</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; leaves A4 and A5 lacking, supplied in photostat.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17152:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17152:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched at Torceter, in the Countie of Northampton the 8. of Iune, Anno Dom. 1588. at the viſitation of the right reuerend Father in God, the Biſhop of Peeterborow, BY <hi>IOHN BEATNIFFE Preacher of the woord of God</hi> in Brackley.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2. Cor. 22.28.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Beſide the thinges which are outward I am cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred daily, and I haue a care ouer all the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON.</hi> Printed by Iohn Charlewood <hi>for Roger VVard.</hi> 1590.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:17152:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17152:2"/>
            <head>To the moſt reuerend Father in God, my Lords grace, Archbiſhop of Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>terbury: Sir <hi>Chriſtopher Hatton</hi> knight, Lord high Chauncellor of England: Sir <hi>William Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil</hi> Knight Lord Burleigh, Lord high Treaſurer of England: Sir <hi>Chriſtopher Wray</hi> Knight, Lord chiefe Iuſtice of England: and to al other which ſincerely fauour the word of God, Grace and Peace be multiplied in Ieſus Chriſt.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mongeſt the manifold calamities and griefes of hart that fall vppon the Church in this old age of the world (right Honorable and welbeloued in the Lord) this is not the leaſt, that the peace of the Church, is daily bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in peeces, and that by ſuch as chalenge to themſelues the name of the Churche, which crie as did the Iewes,<note place="margin">Ier. 7, 4.</note> The Temple of the Lord, the Temple of the Lord: but I feare me, be as Chriſt ſayeth, The
<pb facs="tcp:17152:3"/> congregation of Sathan, for they diſpiſe Rulers,<note place="margin">Reue. 2.9. Iude. 5.8. 2. Tim. 1.4.</note> and ſpeake euill of ſuch as be in aucthority. They de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in queſtions and endles gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alogies, which gender ſtrife rather then Godly edyfying, which is in Faith. Theſe men as they trouble the publique State of the Church, with Schiſmes: ſo doe they alſo diſquiete, the conſciences of many good Soules by making doubts and ambiguities in matters that be moſt plaine and eaſie. They draw ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as they can fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> obedience of the Godly Magiſtrate, denouncing all thoſe to be execrable, curſed and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominable, which bee not of their faction, yea they be growen to ſuch groſneſſe, which they call Puritie, that as they ſay, they dare not defile their cleane vndefiled and regenerat Soules, by ioyning in Praier with ſuch as hold of the reformed ſtate of
<pb facs="tcp:17152:3"/> this Realme. So by this means they deface ſo much as in them is our Church, our Miniſtery, our Orders, and Praiers in the Church. That which they ſay is good, that order which they obſerue is godly how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer it bee: they diſlike all others but themſelues and their followers. But what is this? truly euen the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie practiſe of the falſe apoſtles in the time of <hi>Paul:</hi> for they to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine gentiliſme among the people, defaced <hi>Paul,</hi> and made them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue that hee was not the apoſtle of Chriſt: euen ſo theſe men by the inſtigation of Satan, to ouerthrow our Church and the godly gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof, diſgrace <hi>Paul,</hi> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face our Preachers, and al to wound weake conſciences, and to make co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable themſelues &amp; their new-fangled deuiſes. This their ſiniſter dealing hath done, yea and doth at
<pb facs="tcp:17152:4"/> this day much harm in the church: for beſides the thinges forenamed, it hindereth many good and godly men from dooing that good which they would. I conſidering with my ſelf of the diſpoſition of theſe men, of their manners and marke which they ſhoot at, being by aucthority called to preach at a viſitation of the right reuerende Father in God the Biſhop of Peeterborrow, did there as the time then ſerued my office, &amp; the nature of my Text required re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely defende that which they ſo greatly diſlike, that is, our church and Miniſterie, the order of our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication, and our praiers. Since which time, I haue bin often greatly vrged by dyuers good men, &amp; many of my welwillers to make it publique for the benefite of the whole Church. Seeing their requeſt to be reaſonable, and that my office
<pb facs="tcp:17152:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <add>bindeth me not onely, <hi>exhortari per sanam doctrinam,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Titus 1. verse 9.</note> but also <hi>cotradicere maledicentibus:</hi> I have satisfied their honest request, and suffered it to bee published. Most humblie crauing that your Honors, and all others which fauor the Gospell, and this our godly gouerment under our most gratious Soueraign, to patronize and defende the same, so shall I and others, be the more en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged to execute our offices in the Church.</add>
            </p>
            <p>
               <add>The Lord who is the onely giuer of aucthoritie protect and defende your Honours, to the glorie of his name and the benefite of this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth.</add>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <add>Most desirous of your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours prosperitie, Io. Beatniffe.</add>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:17152:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17152:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <add>THE TEXT.</add>
            </head>
            <q>
               <add>
                  <bibl>1. Peter. Cap 5.2.</bibl>Feede yee the Flocke of God.</add>
            </q>
            <p>
               <add>The holie Ghost by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle S. Peter in these words read unto you (welbeloued in the Lord,) doth set down a commaundement to all Pastours &amp; Ministers, to all those which have cure and charge of soules commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto them, diligently and faithfully to feede the flocke of God.</add>
            </p>
            <p>
               <add>In saying feede the flocke metapho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rically hee exhorteth his fellowe labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, unto whome he speaketh to teach the Church and people of God, with sounde and wholesome doctrine: now, whereas the holy Ghost useth so many figures in so few wordes, hee sheweth what manner of man he would have o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb facs="tcp:17152:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> his flocke, what manner of men hee would have to teach his Church: that is to say, such as be well acquainted with his speeches, such as be learned in the tongues, and thereby be able, not only to exhort with wholsome doctrine but also to couince and stop the mouthes of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersaries, and with facilitie find out the wrettings and false enterpretations of subtil enemies: which doctrine of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ghost, doth impugne &amp; is fully against all those, whatsoever they bee. What countenance soeuer they carie, which would perswade, or beare the worlde in hand, that they be able soundly to teach, and utterly to conuince all erroninous doctrine, Anabaptisticall factions, and Papisticall opinions, and that without art: but what do these men? Verily no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but euen tread under their feete the excellent gifte of God: I mean lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, which is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ordinary meane, which God in his wisedom, hath appointed to true preaching. They set themselues un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to idlenes, and so through their want of skill, (being set forward through a blind</add>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:17152:6"/>
            <p>zeale) they breede iarres in GODS Church, and thereby greeue the Spirite of God, by whome the Children of God are ſealed, vnto the day of redemption.</p>
            <p>Feede, <hi>I.</hi> Metaphorically teach, out of the which word of the Apoſtle, there be foure thinges to be conſidered. Firſt, the care that God hath ouer his Church Second, who they muſt be, that muſte feede. Third, with what they muſt féed. Foure, what they muſt féede.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Where the holy Ghoſt by his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſayth, féede: I gather that he preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth a care ouer his Church, which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth heerein, that he doth not onelie prepare food, but alſo giueth commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that it may be deſtributed in due and equall manner, &amp; procureth meanes from time to time, as I may ſay by ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion; which will faithfully doe and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh theyr Maſters meſſage.</p>
            <p>This is moſte apparant, for when God had choſen his Church, the ſeede of <hi>Abraham,</hi> the choſen <hi>Iſraell:</hi> he did not onely giue them a Lawe, as a Rule to leade them by, and a direction whereby
<pb facs="tcp:17152:7"/> they might walke, the bounds whereof they ſhoulde not paſſe: but alſo, hee ſent foorth his ſeruants the Prophets, whom he did endue with the ſpirite of Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and trewe vnderſtanding, which ſhoulde riſe vp early and late to teach <hi>Iſraell</hi> the ſayde Lawe: which ſhoulde threaten the people with the iudgments of God for theyr tranſgreſſions, which ſhoulde call them to repentaunce, and comfort them in their afflictions: and at the laſt he ſent the trew Prophet, euen his Sonne Ieſus Chriſt, to teach hys Church, and to gather together the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearſed. This proueth the Apoſtle S. <hi>Paul</hi> in theſe wordes. <hi>Diuerſly and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny waies in times paſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 1.1.</note> 
               <hi>ſpake God vnto the Fathers, by Prophets: but laſt of all in theſe dayes, hath hee ſpo kn to vs by his Sonne, whom he hath made heire of all thinges: By whom alſo he made the worlde.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Ieſus in lyke manner ſhewed his care ouer the Church:<note place="margin">Luk. 13.22.</note> for as <hi>Luke</hi> ſayth. <hi>Hee went about through euerie Cittie and euerie Towne, teaching, and
<pb facs="tcp:17152:7"/> making his iourney towards Ieruſalem.</hi> He trauailed from place to place, and by the way as he went, he fedde the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, he taught and declared his Fathers will vnto them: more then that, that his foode might more amply bee deſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted, and this doctrine more liberally be taught, he choſe certaine whome hee called Diſciples,<note place="margin">Math. 10.18</note> and ſent them abroade into all the worlde, and commaunded them to teach all nations.</p>
            <p>After his reſurrection he ſaid to <hi>Peter.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 21.15.</note> 
               <hi>Loueſt thou me?</hi> More then theſe: <hi>feed my flocke.</hi> This he ſpake vnto him that time, thereby to ſignifie vnto <hi>Peter,</hi> the great and tender care that hee had ouer his purchaſed poſſeſſion, which is hys Church.</p>
            <p>After his aſcention, hee called <hi>Paul,</hi> that he might cary his name before the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> before kings, and before the Children of <hi>Iſraell:</hi> thereby ſhewing to vs, that as GOD had gathered his Church, of all eſtates and degrées of people: ſo, he would haue al eſtates and degrées of people to know his will, and
<pb facs="tcp:17152:8"/> alſo haue matter to feede vppon, to the comfort of their ſoules: and therefore in deede <hi>Paul</hi> was very carefull ouer all congregations, and not onely taught diligently himſelfe, but alſo elected and choſe others for the ſame worke: as <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothie,</hi> vnto whom he gaue authority to rule the Church of God at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> and to feede them with wholeſome doctrine. <hi>As I beſought thee to tarry at Epheſus, when I departed into Macedonia:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 1.3.</note> 
               <hi>ſo doe, that thou maieſt commaund ſome that they teach no other doctrine, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that they giue heede, to fables and genealogies which are endleſſe, which breede queſtions, rather then any god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly edifying, which is by faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the ſame effect, hee ſpeaketh vnto his Scholler <hi>Titus,</hi> that he might ſee to the Church. <hi>For this cauſe left I thee in Creta,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Titus. 1.5.</note> 
               <hi>that thou ſhouldeſt continue to redreſſe the thinges that remaine, and ſhouldeſt ordaine elders in euery con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, as I appointed thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This care of God the Father, of hys ſon Chriſt, and of his Apoſtles or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors,
<pb facs="tcp:17152:8"/> doo teach vs which haue cure of ſoules, to be diligent, paynfull and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. You looke now peraduenture, that I ſhoulde make ſome bitter inuectiue ſpeeches againſt Byſhops, which of ſome, are thought not to be ſo careful as their office requireth: but truely I am not ſo determined, for indéede they be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerend fathers: Fathers of the Church, and they be bretheren. I came not he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to accuſe any, I loue it not, I leaue it to the deuill, <hi>qui eſt accuſator fratrum, <hi>which is the accuſer of his bretheren,</hi>
               </hi> and I will ſet it ouer to his adherents, which take pleaſure, and exerciſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues therein day and night. I came he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to doo the office of a Preacher, to to teach the vnlearned, and to put the learned in minde, of thoſe things which they already knowe: and ſo will doe ſo long as I liue, if God permit.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Now it followeth to declare vnto you, who they be that muſt feede. The Apoſtle himſelfe in the firſt verſe of this Chapter declareth. <hi>The Elders</hi> ſayth he,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 5.1.</note> 
               <hi>I beſeech, which am alſo an Elder. Feede
<pb facs="tcp:17152:9"/> the flock of Chriſt.</hi> When he plainely ſpeaketh to thoſe, which haue the office of teaching, and adminiſtring of Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, committed vnto them: and to ſuch, as are thereunto ordinarily and lawfully called.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ierom</hi> deſcribeth vnto vs, foure ſorts of calings. Some ſaith he, were called of God and not by men, as the Prophets and Apoſtles. Others were called of God, and by men: as <hi>Elizeus,</hi> by <hi>Elias.</hi> Others are called by men and not by God, which (ſéeing they haue an ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry calling) they may not be reiected. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers there be, which are neyther ſent by GOD nor man: theſe be the worſt, theſe be Annabaptiſts, theſe runne of a blind zeale &amp; take vppon them to preach without any warrant.</p>
            <p>Of theſe callings one is neceſſary, that is, lawfully to be called by God and man, eſpecially in this our time, wherin we liue vnder a Chriſtian Magiſtrate, without whoſe authority (in my iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) it is not lawfull for any man to execute any office in Church or common
<pb facs="tcp:17152:9"/> wealth. Calling therefore is not to bee deſpiſed, but to bee ſought for: for it is not ynough to haue knowledge in the worde of God, and be able to teach, but alſo to haue calling by the Church, bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond which it is not lawfull to go. Who ſo dooth whatſoeuer hee thinketh of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, <hi>Paul</hi> telleth him plainly what hee is: <hi>Euen ſuch a one,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 5.</note> 
               <hi>of whome we muſt take heede.</hi> For they be dogges, euill la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers, and conciſion. They giue fayre wordes: but ſecretly they bite. They take greate paynes in trotting from houſe to houſe, in making long prayers, in viſiting widdowes houſes, in ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comming the weake: but al is to bréede factions, and to get gaynes vnto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues.</p>
            <p>They call themſelues circumciſion, but the Apoſtle by a pleaſant <hi>proſonemaſia,</hi> caleth them conciſion, ſuch as break and deuide the Church, &amp; ſuch as cut in pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, the vnity and peace of the ſame.<note place="margin">Ier. 23.21.</note> Of theſe ſayth <hi>Ieremie: They did run, but I did not ſend them.</hi> How then can they teach truely? they cannot: for the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle
<pb facs="tcp:17152:10"/> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> aſketh this queſtion. <hi>Howe can they preach except they be ſent?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 10.15.</note> as though he ſhould ſay they cannot. And therefore he ſayth to <hi>Titus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tit. 1.5.</note> 
               <hi>For this cauſe haue I left thee in Creta, that thou ſhouldeſt ordaine Elders in euery con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, as I haue appointed thee.</hi> As though he ſhoulde ſay, <hi>leaſt any ſhoulde take vnto himſelfe honour,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 5 5.</note> 
               <hi>but he that is called: I haue left thee there for that purpoſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They which haue this calling, God proſpereth their labours: they which haue it not, (thoughe they haue the words of fayth in their mouth) yet they bring foorth no fruite, for they ſee not that which is good, but euen as it were to leade men by the eares, to their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſſe opinions.</p>
            <p>Feede ye, heere is ſecondly noted vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, who they bee that muſt feede the flocke of God: <hi>The elders</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi> The Greeke worde is Πρεςβυτερος, which the Apoſtle vſeth: which word of two ſortes of people is falſlie interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Of the Papiſts, which would haue
<pb facs="tcp:17152:10"/> it to ſignifie a ſacrifiſing, or a maſſing Prieſt. Of an other ſort, which woulde haue it onely to ſignifie Lay-men: but the Apoſtle heere confuteth them both, for he ſpeaketh not of ſacrifiſing preiſts, neither yet of lay men: but of ſuch as ſhoulde guide and teach his Church, therefore the worde <hi>(Elders)</hi> ſignifyeth heere, Biſhops &amp; Miniſters. Of whome the office of the firſt is, not only to teach, but alſo to rule the Church of God, to keepe it in with a Biſhop-like authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: this <hi>Paul</hi> prooueth. <hi>Take heede vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your ſelues, and to the whole flocke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 20.</note> 
               <hi>ouer the which the holy Ghoſt hath made you ouerſeeers, to rule the Church of God, which he hath purchaſed with his owne bloode.</hi> Out of which wordes I gather thus much, that of the one ſide, as a Biſhop is not exempted from the office of teaching becauſe hee is a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop: ſo, on the other ſide, hee is not cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a Biſhop, becauſe he is apt to teach, neither for the office of teaching, but for the preheminence of ruling and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſéeing of the Church of God: that falſe
<pb facs="tcp:17152:11"/> doctrine come not in, that offenders, which corrupt the manners and peace of the Church, may bee puniſhed, and ſuch like. The office of the other is this, to teach and to adminiſter the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: according to the ſaying of Chriſt generally to all miniſters. <hi>Goe into all the worlde,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 28.</note> 
               <hi>teach all nations, and bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize them, in the name of the father, and of the ſonne, and of the holie Ghoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>Paul</hi> ſayth: <hi>Preach thou the worde: bee feruent in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon: reproue, rebuke &amp; exhort with al loue patience &amp; doctrine.</hi> The which places beeing with diſretion conſidered of, are ſufficient to prooue, that as on the one ſide, calling is neceſſary: ſo, they which be called, muſt bee ſuch as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle heere ſpeaketh of, <hi>(Elders)</hi> that is to ſay, Biſhops to rule and to teach: Miniſters, to teach, to adminiſter, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke and to exhort, where they be there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto lawfully called.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
               <hi>(Feede ye)</hi> heere is thirdly to be noted with what they muſt feede? verily with the word, with it haue all the Prophets
<pb facs="tcp:17152:11"/> fed: that ſame is the nouriſhment of the Church. S. <hi>Peter</hi> ſayth: <hi>We are borne agayne, not of corruptible ſeede,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>but of incorruptible, by the word of God, who liuech and endureth for euer. For all fleſh is graſſe, and the glory of man is as the flower of gras: the graſſe withereth, and the flower falleth away, but the word of the Lord indureth for euer and this is the worde which is preached a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you.</hi> By which ſaying it is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt that the onely woord of God ought to be taught in the church, and that they are not to be heard which would bring in mens deuiſes into the Church: God hath not permitted ſo much to any mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall man: neither may the Church bee gouerned or fed by any other word then by the worde of God, by the which it is begotten and borne.</p>
            <p>This confuteth the Papiſts, which would haue the Church to be of greater authoritie then the woord, which can not poſſibly be, for the Church is groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vppon the doctrine of the Prophets and Apoſtles, Chriſt himſelfe the head
<pb facs="tcp:17152:12"/> corner ſtone: ſo that it is againſt the woord, that the houſe, that is to ſay, the church, ſhould rule the maiſter, that is to ſay, the woord: and it is againſt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> daughter namely the church ſhould rule hir Mother, which is the woord.</p>
            <p>Hereuppon it followeth that the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters muſt onely feede with the word of God,<note place="margin">Eze, 3.17.</note> and with no other. God ſayth, <hi>thou ſhalt heare words from my mouth, and thou ſhalt warne others from mee.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 1.7. Math. 28.</note> 
               <hi>I haue put my words in thy mouth, and what ſo euer I haue commaunded thee, that ſhalt thou ſpeake,</hi> and did binde his Diſciples to a certain kinde of doctrine, namely to teach thoſe things which hee had commaunded them: whereby wee learn that onely the woord of God muſt be taught in the Church, and no other. When I ſay that the only word of God muſt be taught, I do not therby as ſome do, condemne the reading or alledging of the Fathers, for that were altogether curioſitie, I am not of that minde, I thinke them very neceſſarie to bee read
<pb facs="tcp:17152:12"/> and alledged, not as doctrine of ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but as confirmation of iudgement: for when our iudgements, &amp; the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the fathers are one, vpon ſome place of Scripture, then we ſay it is <hi>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem ſpiritus,</hi> one and the ſelfe ſame ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: ſo that alledging of the Fathers is not to be blamed, but bringing in mans doctrine as neceſſarie to ſaluation, in ſtead of the woord of God, which onely ſerueth to that ende is woorthily to bee condemned: where it is ſaid, feede, and that with the woord. There is rendred a reaſon, becauſe the written woord of God containeth in it all things neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to ſaluation, and alſo to life and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and therefore that we neede not ſeek any further for the aſſurance of the ſame, this prooueth <hi>Iohn</hi> the Apoſtle:<note place="margin">Iohn. 21</note> 
               <hi>Many things did Ieſus in the ſight of his diſciples which are not writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in this booke, but theſe things are written, that Ieſus Chriſt is the Sonne of God, &amp; that in beleeuing yee might haue eternall life.</hi> The other prooueth <hi>Paul:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Tim. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Euery Scripture giuen by inſpiration is profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
<pb facs="tcp:17152:13"/> to teach, to reprooue, and to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort, that the man of God may be made perfect vnto euerie good woorke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 15.</note>Therefore ſearch the Scriptures, for in them yee hoope to haue eternall life.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Laſtly it is to bee declared what they muſt feed, n. the Church. There be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſorts of Churches, there is a viſible Church and an inuiſible Church: there is a militant Church, and a triumphant Church: there is a true Church, &amp; there is a falſe Church. Now where the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſaith, <hi>feede the flocke of God,</hi> hee putteth a difference betwixt the true &amp; falſe Church: now a Church is nothing els but a company of people gathered together, ſo that euery company is a Church, but euery company is not a church of God. Moreouer this is to bee obſerued, that whereas the Apoſtle ſaith <hi>feed the flock of God,</hi> and that the flock of God is partly viſible, partly inuiſible, as is aforeſaid, that hee meaneth, that the miniſters of the word ſhould dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently feed all the flocke of God vppon the earth: which is flatly againſt thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:17152:13"/> that would ſingle out the church of God from the reſt, not knowing that there bee ſome which though they do not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare outwardly, yet are they moſt dear and precious in the ſight of the Lord: I muſt bee plaine with you, it is a great fault in this our time, wee will haue none to be of the Church but ſuch as we like, ſuch as follow our fantaſies: &amp; ſuch as will not, we vtterly condemne them, whereas there bee many hundreds, yea many thouſands beſides vs: this was <hi>Elias</hi> fault. <hi>O Lord</hi> ſaith he, <hi>they haue broken down thy Altars, and ſlaine thy Prophets, and I onely am left, and they ſeeke my life to take it away:</hi> he thought there had not bin left vpon the earth one man that feared God but himſelfe: but marke <hi>reſponſum Domini,</hi> harke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> what the Lord ſaith:<note place="margin">Reg. 19.18.</note> 
               <hi>I haue reſerued to my ſelfe ſeuen thouſand men that neuer bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed their knees to Baal:</hi> mark this wel, there be more of the church then we bee aware of: therefore let vs feed in hope and labor in hope, incoraging all, diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raging none: but let vs feede the flocke
<pb facs="tcp:17152:14"/> of God viſible and inuiſible, true &amp; falſe.</p>
            <p>Of theſe two Churches it is neceſſary to ſpeake a litle, beginning with the falſe church, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the other may be the better diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned: the falſe church I cal thoſe which either openly ſet their ſelues againſt the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God, or thoſe which perſwade themſelues that they be of the church &amp; are not: of both theſe ſorts ther be many.</p>
            <p>The one ſort, are they of whom <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpeaketh of.<note place="margin">Pſalm. 26.</note> 
               <hi>I haue hath hated the congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the wicked, and I wil not ſit with the vngodlie.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Numb. 15,</note> Such were <hi>Corah, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> and the two hundred and fifty men that were with them, men of renowne and famous in the congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation.<note place="margin">Gene. 11.</note> Such were they that builded <hi>Babel:</hi> euery of theſe were a congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, a church, but a falſe church, a church that openly fighteth and ſetteth it ſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Church of God. The other ſort, are they, which bragge that they be the ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> the children of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, but they deceiue themſelues, for they do not the works of <hi>Abraham,</hi> they ſpeak much, but they do litle: they look
<pb facs="tcp:17152:14"/> like Lambes but they bee rauenning Wolues: outwardly they appeare bew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull, but inwardly they be full of dead mens bones. <hi>He is not a Iew which is a Iew outward,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 2.</note> 
               <hi>but hee is a Iew which is hid within.</hi> Of theſe face-makers, and outward Religious perſons ſpeaketh <hi>Leo: Eccleſiae nomine armamini, ſed contra eccleſiam demicatis:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Leo.</note> yee arme your ſelues with the name of the church, but yee fight agaynſt the Church.</p>
            <p>Theſe ſay they are Iewes, but they are not, but are the congregation of Satan. Theſe be the falſe church,<note place="margin">Reg. 2.9.</note> theſe muſt be taught, if at any time God will giue them grace to repent, that they may be brought to the true church, and ſo be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in the day of the Lord. Now let vs proceed vnto the true church, which is in God, hereby it is knowen, it is not in man, but in GOD, this is the true church, this is the ſociety of all the true faithfull ſainctes and elect of God. This church conſiſteth of Faith, Hope, Loue, and of the Spirit of Chriſt. This we cal the catholicke church which is ſpread o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb facs="tcp:17152:15"/> the face of the whole world. Then the catholicke church is not at Rome: no, no, they are much deceiued that ſay ſo, or beleeue ſo, it is not tyed to one place or to one people: but it is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of all the faithfull, that haue bene from the beginning of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, that are now, &amp; ſhalbe vnto the end of the world: <hi>Ierom</hi> ſayth <hi>Eccleſia Chriſti in toto or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be eccleſias poſſidens, ſpiritus vnitate coniuncta eſt, &amp; habet vrbes legis &amp; prophetarum, euangelij &amp; apoſtolorum: non eſt egreſſa de finibus ſuis, i. de ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turis:</hi> The church of Chriſt which poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſeth all the churches in the world, is ioyned together in the vnity of the ſpirit, and it hath the cities of the law and of the Prophets, of the Goſpell, and of the Apoſtles, it doth not goe beyonde her boundes, that is the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>This Church hath in it pure and ſounde doctrine, euen the ſame which came from Chriſte, and ſent abroade throughout all the worlde by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, which excludeth all other doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines and precepts of man, it hath alſo
<pb facs="tcp:17152:15"/> the true and liuely vſe of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, it hath vnity and catholicke con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent touching the chéef points of chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an religion. This church (becauſe it of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten erreth, ſometime by ignorance as <hi>Paul</hi> before his conuerſion,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 1.13.</note> ſometime by temptations as <hi>Abraham</hi> when for feare of his life he fel to diſſembling, or by infirmitie,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 10.4</note> as <hi>Dauid</hi> when hee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted adulterie,) ought to bee fed with doctrine, and be kept in with wholſome correction. And therefore ouer this church hath God placed Biſhops, and hath commaunded them to ouerſee it, and to feed it faithfully and dilligently. let thoſe therefore watch that they may giue their fellow ſeruants meat in due ſeaſon. <hi>Bleſſed is that Seruant whome hys Maiſter ſhall find ſo doing.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 24.</note> 
               <hi>Verily I ſay vnto you, he will make him ruler o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer all his goods.</hi> Therefore feed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> flock, this appertaineth to vs miniſters: God hath made vs paſtors, and wee haue a flocke, euen a church in God the father, begotten of the word, born of the word, and now muſt be nouriſhed, brought vp
<pb facs="tcp:17152:16"/> and inſtructed by the word.</p>
            <p>That wee haue ſuch a church here in England as I haue here deſcribed, there is no queſtion at all to be made, neither do the godly doubt of it. But for the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter comfort of the church, and that they may haue in a readines at all times to ſtop the mouth of the Anabaptiſt, to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrow the Papiſt, and tread vnder feet the Secturian. I wil prooue it moſt plainly by the way of an argument, where the Goſpell is truly preached, where the Sacraments be according to Chriſt his inſtitution reuerently admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred, where there is vnitie, and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke conſente touching the cheefe points of chriſtian religion, wher Chriſt is acknowledged the head of the church, there is the true church in God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: but the church of England hath, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, holdeth and acknowledgeth al theſe things, <hi>ergo</hi> in England there is a true church in God the Father.</p>
            <p>The chiefeſt reaſons that the Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſtes Papiſtes and Sciſmatickes vſe in defacing of our church are theſe:
<pb facs="tcp:17152:16"/> firſt that our miniſters bee not lawfully called: <hi>2.</hi> that we want diſcipline: <hi>3.</hi> that wee haue no lawfull prayers in our church, and therefor no church.</p>
            <p>Theſe reaſons though they be weake, and moſt weake, yet are they péeuiſh and very daungerous: and therefore I thinke it neceſſarie to confute them.</p>
            <p>Touching the firſt wher they ſay we haue not a lawful miniſtery: I anſwere, we haue, yea and ſuch a miniſtery as is ſent of God, and lawfully called by man. I prooue it thus: whereſoeuer there is a Church in God the Father, there is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo a lawful miniſterie. But wee haue a Church in God the Father as before is prooued, <hi>ergo,</hi> a lawful miniſterie. This argument in plainly prooued by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> words of <hi>Ieremie.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 3.14.15.</note> 
               <hi>O yee diſobedient Children turne againe</hi> ſayth the Lord, <hi>for I am you Lord, and I will take you, one of a Cittie, and two of a Tribe, and will bring you to Sion, and I will giue you Paſtors according to mine owne hart, which ſhall feede you with knowledge &amp; vnderſtanding.</hi> Marke here, he ſaith
<pb facs="tcp:17152:17"/> he will chooſe them one of a Cittie, and two of a Tribe, and hée will bring them into Sion, that is, into his Church: hee will giue them paſtors after his owne hart, theſe be lawful I trow, for he choo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth none but thoſe that bee meete, you may knowe them, for they feede with knowledge and vnderſtanding. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wee do thus in the church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land or no, iudge yee.</p>
            <p>Touching the ſecond, that wee want diſcipline &amp; therefore we are no church. I deny the argument, but they ſay wee haue not the diſcipline of the primatiue Church, therefore no church.</p>
            <p>It is a <hi>non ſequitur,</hi> for although we haue not the diſcipline of the primatiue Church, yet wee haue diſcipline: and therefore they ſlaunder vs. But alaſſe, theſe men that ſay ſo, they knowe not what they ſay: for diſcipline is no eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall part of the church: men and women be the Church, not diſcipline, ſo that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline is a wall about a citie, or a hedge aboute a vineyard, wherof though a peece ſometime be broken downe, yet a
<pb facs="tcp:17152:17"/> citie, yet a vineyard. I graunt diſcipline to be as neceſſary in the church, to kéepe the people within the railes of <hi>Moſes,</hi> law, as a wall about a cittie to defende the citizens from the force of their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie: and for my part, I know none that denieth it, but onely thoſe that make the moſt to doo about it: wee haue ſo much that they them ſelues complayne &amp; crye out of it. I maruell what they would do, if we had that which they themſelues ſéeke for. I cannot tel what they would haue: wee fynd fault with the ſinnes of the people, wee excommunicate notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous offendors, if you aſke by what au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, I anſwere euen as <hi>Paul</hi> did,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 1.20.</note> ſo do we. <hi>Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Alexander</hi> haue made ſhipwracke of faith, <hi>quos ego tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didi Satanae vt diſcant, non blaſphemare:</hi> whom I (ſaith he) haue deliuered to Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than that they might learne not to blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme: It is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iudgement of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beſt lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that euer I read of,<note place="margin">Act. 5.</note> that <hi>Peeter</hi> did excommunicate <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphira,</hi> after the which they yéelded vp y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ghoſt.</p>
            <p>I would here for my learning very
<pb facs="tcp:17152:18"/> gladly know who did helpe <hi>Paul</hi> or <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> to exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municat, becauſe theſe ſlaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers of our Church do ſay, it is not lawful for any man to excommunicate. If it had not bin lawfull, ſurely <hi>Paul</hi> would not haue done it, neither yet <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Tertulian</hi> ſayth, that excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,<note place="margin">Tertul. in Apolog.</note> or ſeperation from the Church, was in his time, which was thirteeene hundreth yeares agone in the handes of the Biſhops, and of the Prieſtes. <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen</hi> commaundeth him that hath bene thriſe admoniſhed,<note place="margin">Orig. hom. 7. an. Ioſ.</note> and will not repent to be cut of from the body of the church, <hi>per eccleſiae preſides,</hi> or by the rulers of the church, wher alſo he declareth what theſe rulers are: for ſayth he, the prieſts ſparing one that had offended, and neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting their prieſtly authority, did goe about the diſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the whole church, ſo that <hi>Origen</hi> thought it was a decay to the Church, that excommunicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhould goe out of the handes of the Prieſtes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Euſeb. lib. 6. cap. 34.</note>
               <hi>Euſebius</hi> ſheweth, that <hi>Fabian</hi> did ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate <hi>Philip</hi> the Emperour.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:17152:18"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Ambroſe</hi> did excommunicate <hi>Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi> the Emperour,<note place="margin">Trip. hiſto. lib. 9. cap. 30.</note> for that ſlaughter which was done in <hi>Theſſalonica, anno Dom.</hi> 391. &amp; is at this day greatly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended therefore of the learned, &amp; god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Theſe examples prooue the lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of our excommunication, which is practiſed vppon ſuch like occaſions, and is alſo executed by ſuch kind of meanes, and therfore not to be found fault with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, neither yet that our church ſhould be ſlaundered either for the want of it, either yet for the practiſe of that which wee haue. Touching the third, wheras they ſay, wée haue no lawful prayers in our Churche, and therefore no Church: that is a moſt abhominable ſlaunder, &amp; not to bee tollerated. Of theſe kinde of people that ſay ſo, there be two ſortes: the one be the Papiſtes, and they come in with their old lying antiquityes, and ſay that the ſeruice in the church of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland is nothing lyke to the vſe of the primitiue Church, for it hath no ſet or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of prayers, ſaue a little imitation of the old Mattins and Euenſong, and that
<pb facs="tcp:17152:19"/> in Schiſme and hereſie, and therefore not onely vnprofitable, but alſo dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable. The other ſort they ſay that there be no praiers at al in the church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande (they ſay ſo in effecte) for they ſay we do all read praiers already made to our hands, which by their ſayings, are no prayers, neither yet do edifie at all, for (ſay they) reading is but bare féeding yea and as all as playing vpon a ſtage, and worſe too. But to theſe I anſwere as I did before they ſlander the church, for wée pray truly as God hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded in his word, and as our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt hath taught vs we pray to God the Father, and to none but to him onely. Wee come to him in the name of his ſonne Ieſus Chriſt, and in his name onely, and therefore I conclude that we pray truely. Thus haue I as God hath mooued me, and at this time hath affoor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vnto me, declared vnto you the ſence and meaning of this holy Scripture.</p>
            <p>The Lord graunt that it may worke that which I looke for, that is the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uancement of Gods glory, a zeale and
<pb facs="tcp:17152:19"/> care of Gods miniſters ouer the flocke of God committed vnto them. The flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing eſtate of the Goſpel of Ieſus Chriſt, and the vnitie, peace, and quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the church, that antichriſtianity and factio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s being defaced, we may with one hart and one voice glorifie God the Father in this world, and in the world to come raigne with him eternally by the meanes of his Sonne Ieſus Chriſt: to whom with the Father and the holy Ghoſt be al praiſe, glory, dominion, and power both now and for euer, world without end Amen.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
